Preliminary Guide to the Emma Joy Dana Collection of Anna Mackova
Yale University Arts Library
Emma Joy Dana collection of Anna Mackova
1906-1960
AOB 31
Yale University Arts Library
5.5
12 boxes
The collection documents the graphic design career of Anna Macková.
Dana, Emma Joy
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Emma Joy Dana, 2005.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Anna Macková (1887-1969) worked in Czechoslovakia in the early to mid 20th century. After art school, Macková took commissions and made print and bookplate portfolios. Her work was early on influenced by traditional folk art designs and art nouveau. Over the years, Macková developed her own distinctive and more naturalistic style. She skillfully depicted animals, flowers, and landscape scenes. Macková had a longtime romantic relationship with artist Josef Vachal.
Scope and Contents
The collection documents the graphic design career of Anna Macková. It consists of biographical materials, including some clippings and exhibition pamphlets collected by Macková herself, as well as a variety of graphic works, drawing and paintings, and decorative boxes by Macková. The collection also includes a selection of prints by other artists, including a portrait of Macková by J. Vachal.
Arrangement
Organized into six series: I. Biographical Materials. II. Illustrated Books. III. Boxes. IV. Drawings and Paintings. V. Prints. VI. Ex-Libris. Within each series, materials are arranged chronologically.
The designation "VRT" indicates vertical file storage.
Bookplates, Czech; Prints -- 20th Century -- Czechoslovakia; Graphic arts -- Czechoslovakia; Macková, Anna, 1887-1969; Váchal, Josef, 1884-1969
- Biographical Materials, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This section contains clippings and exhibition pamphlets, some collected by Macková.
  - Scrapbook pages, 1916-1919 (Box 1)
  - Exhibition checklist, 1921 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook pages, 1922-1923 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook pages, 1924 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook pages, 1925-1926 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook pages, 1927-1928 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook pages, 1929-1930 (Box 1)
  - Exhibition announcement, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook page, undated (Box 1)
  - National Ornament in Czechoslovak Schools, undated (Box 1)
- Illustrated Books, Series II
  - Koleda, 1921 (Box 1)
  - Kozlička, 1922 (Box 1)
  - Prázdninové Putování, 1927 (Box 1)
- Boxes, Series III
  Macková created decorative boxes to hold small prints, drawings, and ex-libris. The boxes also contained loose prints and ex-libris which are in Series V. Prints and Series VI. Ex-Libris. The works have been separated from the boxes for preservation reasons.
  - From box with landscape scene on front cover, 1915-1959 (Box 11)
    - Drawings, 1916-1919 (Box 2)
    - Drawings, 1934-1949 undated (Box 2)
    - Ex-Libris, 1915; 18 (Box 2)
    - Ex-Libris, 1916; 6 (Box 2)
    - Ex-Libris, 1917; 14 (Box 2)
    - Ex-Libris, 1918; 10 (Box 2)
    - Ex-Libris, 1919; 16 (Box 2)
    - Ex-Libris, 1920; 15 (Box 2)
    - Ex-Libris, 1921; 11 (Box 2)
    - Ex-Libris, 1922; 16 (Box 2)
    - Ex-Libris, 1923; 7 (Box 2)
    - Ex-Libris, 1924; 6 (Box 3)
    - Ex-Libris, 1925; 8 (Box 3)
    - Ex-Libris, 1926; 10 (Box 3)
    - Ex-Libris, 1927; 3 (Box 3)
    - Ex-Libris, 1928; 12 (Box 3)
    - Ex-Libris, 1929; 2 (Box 3)
    - Ex-Libris, 1930; 9 (Box 3)
    - Ex-Libris, 1931; 2 (Box 3)
    - Ex-Libris, 1933; 1 (Box 3)
    - Ex-Libris, 1934; 4 (Box 3)
    - Ex-Libris, 1935; 4 (Box 3)
    - Ex-Libris, 1936; 5 (Box 3)
    - Ex-Libris, 1937; 4 (Box 3)
    - Ex-Libris, 1938; 5 (Box 3)
    - Ex-Libris, 1940; 1 (Box 3)
    - Ex-Libris, 1941; 6 (Box 3)
    - Ex-Libris, 1942; 1 (Box 3)
    - Ex-Libris, 1943; 14 (Box 3)
    - Ex-Libris, 1944; 6 (Box 3)
    - Ex-Libris, 1945; 3 (Box 3)
    - Ex-Libris, 1946; 16 items (Box 4)
    - Ex-Libris, 1947; 8 items (Box 4)
    - Ex-Libris, 1948; 5 items (Box 4)
    - Ex-Libris, 1949; 6 items (Box 4)
    - Ex-Libris, 1950; 1 item (Box 4)
    - Ex-Libris, 1952; 1 item (Box 4)
    - Ex-Libris, 1953; 3 items (Box 4)
    - Ex-Libris, 1954; 4 items (Box 4)
    - Ex-Libris, 1955; 3 items (Box 4)
    - Ex-Libris, 1956; 1 item (Box 4)
    - Ex-Libris, 1959; 1 item (Box 4)
    - Ex-Libris, undated; 7 items (Box 4)
  - From box with patchwork image cover, 1913-1960 (Box 12)
    - Printed ephemera, 1913; 1 (Box 4)
    - Printed ephemera, 1917; 1 (Box 4)
    - Printed ephemera, 1918; 1 (Box 4)
    - Printed ephemera, 1919-1920; 2 (Box 4)
    - Printed ephemera, 1921; 1 (Box 4)
    - Printed ephemera, 1924; 5 (Box 4)
    - Printed ephemera, 1926; 4 (Box 4)
    - Printed ephemera, 1927; 4 (Box 4)
    - Printed ephemera, 1928; 3 (Box 4)
    - Printed ephemera, 1930; 3 (Box 4)
    - Printed ephemera, 1943; 2 (Box 4)
    - Printed ephemera, 1944; 3 (Box 4)
    - Printed ephemera, 1960; 1 (Box 4)
    - Printed ephemera, undated; 5 (Box 4)
- Drawings and Paintings, Series IV
  This section contains examples of painting and drawing by Macková.
  - Watercolors, 1906-1909; 14 (Box 9)
  - Watercolors from art school, 1909-1910; 19 (Box 9)
  - Watercolors, 1910-1919; 24 (Box 9)
  - Watercolors, circa 1920s; 5 (Box 9)
  - Watercolor exhibition poster, 1930; 1 (Box 8)
  - Watercolors, circa 1940s; 2 (Box 9)
  - Watercolors, circa 1950s; 10 (Box 9)
  - Watercolors, undated; 1 (Box 9)
  - Sketchbook, 1930s-1950s; 1 (Box 5)
  - Korčula Portfolio, 1923
    General note
    See Series V.
- Prints, Series V
  This section contains individual prints and portfolios. Untitled works are given a descriptive title in brackets. See also Series III. Boxes and Series VI. Ex-Libris for other printed materials.
  - Prints by others, 1922 (Box 5)
    Includes a portrait of Macková by J. Vachal.
  - Individual Prints
    - Prints, 1916-1919; 11 (Box 5)
    - New Year's greetings, 1920-1952; 12 (Box 5)
    - Prints, 1920s; 13 (Box 5)
    - Prints, 1920s; 4 (Box 10)
      - [interior], 1923 (Box 10)
      - [steeple in landscape], 1925 (Box 9)
      - [church], 1926 (Box 10)
      - [pine trees in landscape – warm palette], 1926 (Box VRT)
      - [windmills], 1927 (Box 10)
      - [snow-capped trees in blue], 1929 (Box VRT)
    - Prints, 1930s; 10 (Box 5)
    - Prints, 1930s; 1 (Box 10)
      - [mushrooms], 1932 (Box VRT)
      - [Vachal portrait], 1934 (Box VRT)
      - [cyclamen], 1936 (Box VRT)
      - [landscape with swirling clouds], 1936 (Box VRT)
      - [lily of the valley], 1936 (Box 10)
      - [pansies], 1937 (Box 9)
    - Prints, 1945 1954; 2 (Box 5)
    - Prints, undated; 14 (Box 5)
      - [village], undated (Box 9)
  - Portfolios
    - Domažlice, 1917; 4; folded sheets (Box 5)
    - Zčeských Krajů, 1920; 1 folded sheet; 8 prints (Box 5)
    - Korčula, 1923-1924; 23 (Box 8)
    - Českémoîivy Deseî Dřevoryîů, 1926; 10 (Box 10)
    - [Prázdninové putování], 1927; 26 (Box 10)
    - Bulharské Mlŷny, 1927; 12 (Box 10)
    - Prášilská Papírna, 1930-1931; 5 folded text pages; 6 prints (Box 8)
    - Drobnà Užitko Và Grafika, 1929; 15; folded sheets (Box 5)
    - Druhá Ročenka, 1934; bound (Box 5)
- Ex-Libris, Series VI
  This section contains both ex-libris portfolios as well as individual bookplates.
  - Portfolios
    - Scrapbook, 1915-1930 (Box 6)
    - 20 Ex-Libris, 1924 (Box 6)
    - XX Ex-Libris, 1928 (Box 6)
    - Ex-Libris, novoročenky a drobnà grafika, 1952 (Box 6)
  - Individual Items
    - Bookplates, 1915-1919; 21 (Box 7)
    - Bookplates, 1920-1923; 16 (Box 7)
    - Bookplates, 1925-1928; 23 (Box 7)
    - Bookplates, 1930-1937; 15 (Box 7)
    - Bookplates, 1938; 17 (Box 7)
    - Bookplates, 1941-1943; 18 (Box 7)
    - Bookplates, 1944-1946; 27 (Box 7)
    - Bookplates, 1947-1949; 6 (Box 7)
    - Bookplates, 1953-1959; 10 (Box 7)
    - Bookplates, undated; 16 (Box 7)
    - Bookplates, undated; 15 (Box 7)
    - Bookplates, undated; 15 (Box 7)
    - Bookplates, undated; 17 (Box 7)